# Jalaj Maheshwari, MS

(267)-252-4048 | jalajm@alumni.upenn.edu | www.jalajmaheshwari.com| www.linkedin.com/in/jalajmaheshwari

#### PERSONAL STATEMENT

My interests are in applications of computer vision and deep learning in autonomous systems and robotics. Have over **3+ years** of work experience and have demonstrated the capability to work in a team and as an individual contributor, with excellent communication skills, and strong technical, presentation, and organizational skills.

#### **RELEVANT EXPERIENCE**

#### RESEARCH ENGINEER I

# Center for Injury Research and Prevention, Children's Hospital of Philadelphia, PA, USA

May 2016 - Present

- Analyzed simulator driving data to calculate reaction times in an autonomous vehicle to manual takeover scenario.
- Designed sled system to study occupant startle in lateral swerving using Arduino, relays, and motion capture systems.

# Real-Time Facial Detection, Cognitive Loading, and Driver Distraction Estimation

- Built a pipeline to detect faces in real-time using a webcam; Incorporating facial keypoint detection using deep learning.
- Working on estimating cognitive load and driver distraction for safer driving.

## **Behavioral Cloning**

- Programmed a convolutional neural network (CNN) to train a car to drive in a simulator using Keras and OpenCV.
- Used optimization techniques to generalize driving on multiple tracks and achieved full performance in training environment.

# **Traffic Sign Classification**

- Built and trained a deep neural network to classify GTSRB dataset using TensorFlow and OpenCV.
- Experimented with different network architectures; Implemented data augmentation to achieve greater performance.

#### **Vehicle Detection and Tracking**

- Trained a machine learning model (SVM) to identify vehicles in an image.
- Created a vehicle detection and tracking pipeline using heatmaps; Evaluated model on video data from a vehicle on a highway.

#### Advanced Lane Detection on Roads using Computer Vision

- Coded a lane-finding algorithm using robust image processing (distortion correction, color transforms, and gradient threshold).
- Identified lane curvature and vehicle position relative to highway lane.

#### RESEARCH ASSISTANT

## mLab, PRECISE, University of Pennsylvania, PA, USA

Sep 2017 - Sep 2018

- Developed F1Tenth, a 1/10<sup>th</sup> size autonomous race car incorporating perception, planning, and control algorithms.
- Integrated localization, sensor fusion (IMU, LIDAR, visual odometry, wheel encoders), path planning, and control using ROS.

# Localization of Lost Vehicle using a Particle Filter

- Implemented a 2D particle filter capable of localizing a vehicle within desired accuracy and time.
- Utilized noisy initial location, sensor and control data to make estimate of position.

#### Sensor Fusion: Unscented Kalman Filter (UKF)

- Incorporated a constant turn rate and velocity model to detect bicycle moving around vehicle.
- Combined LIDAR and RADAR data inputs to determine absolute position; Calculated error with respect to ground truth.

# • PRODUCT DESIGN AND DEVELOPMENT ENGINEER - INTERN

# The Ford Motor Company, MI, USA

Jun 2017 - Sep 2017

- 3D scanned a booster child restraining seat to generate 3D CAD model.
- Fixed generated model in CAD software, and validated full working model against physical crash test data.

# **EDUCATION**

# **Self-Driving Car Nanodegree**

Aug 2017 - May 2018

Udacity Online Coursework

# University of Pennsylvania, USA

Master of Science in Engineering (M.S.E.) Mechanical Engineering and Applied Mechanics Aug 2015 - May 2017

#### Birla Institute of Technology & Science - Pilani, INDIA

Bachelor of Engineering (Hons.) (B.E) Mechanical Engineering Aug 2011 - July 2015

#### SKILLS